Inventory of the Virginia Cole Trenholm Papers, 1929-1979
University of Wyoming. American Heritage Center.
- PHOTOGRAPHS:
  - Arapaho:
    - Chief Washakie. Painting by Henry H. Cross (PHOTO (B-W27))
    - Louis Bordeaux, standing first on left, was an interpreter and a son of James Bordeaux. Left to right: Spotted Tail, Swift Bear, Sitting Bull and Red Cloud (PHOTO (B-B644-L))
    - Mary Julia Bordeaux in her tribal costume (PHOTO (B-B644-L))
    - Signing of the McLaughlin Agreement (PHOTO (B-W27-f))
    - Southern Arapahoes in Council, near Colony, Oklahoma (PHOTO (In2-tri-arap))
  - Footprints:
    - Bridger's Ferry (Orin) on the Platte River (PHOTO (R524-pla))
    - Hi Kelly Ranch (PHOTO (R151-hter))
    - Johnson County Cattle Raiders, Prisoners at Ft. D. A. Russell, 1892 (PHOTO (W994-jew))
    - The Johnson County Invaders. Mike Shonsey (kneeling) third from left, second row. An odd assortment of Wyoming cattlemen and Texas gunmen (PHOTO (W994-jew))
    - Major Powell, officer commanding in the "Wagon Box" fight. "Portugee Phillips" who made the famous ride from Ft. Kearney to Ft. Laramie in 1866 (PHOTO (F775-bol))
    - Old Bedlam (about 1880) (PHOTO (F775-La-h-eh))
  - The Agency House at Darlington (Okla) (PHOTO (Ok4-t-dar))
  - American Horse, Sioux Chief (PHOTO (B-Am35ho))
  - An Arapaho village of tepees in Whitewood Canyon, Wyoming, in 1870. (PHOTO (In2-tri-arap))
  - Arapaho Camp (PHOTO (In2-tri-arap))
  - Arapaho chief and Sub-chiefs with James Irwin Super-intendent at Fort Washakie. "They came with pipes to sue for peace. Note Black Coal's right hand with fingers missing" (PHOTO (In2-tri-arap))
  - Arapaho Ghost Shirt, Showing Coloring (PHOTO (In2-co))
  - Arapaho Moccassin (PHOTO (In2-co))
  - Arapaho Sundance, 1938 (PHOTO (In2-da))
  - Arapaho Sundance, 1938 (PHOTO (In2-da))
  - Arapahoes at Estes Park (Oliver Toll Trip), July 1913 (PHOTO (In2-tri-arap))
  - At the Old Government Sawmill, Esterbrook (PHOTO (W994-Fest))
  - Basin Indian home near Dayton, Nevada (PHOTO (In2))
  - Belknap Reservation, Montana, Gros Ventre Camp (PHOTO (In2-res-bel))
  - Bellewood Hotel, Glendo (PHOTO (W994-t-gl))
  - Black Coal (PHOTO (B-B561co))
  - Black Coyote's wife (PHOTO (B-B562-c))
  - Black Coyote (Watan-gaa), a Southern Arapaho, Captain of Indian Police, School Commissioner, Deputy U.S. Sheriff, Marshal, a noted leader of the Ghost Dance, delegate to Washington in 1898 (PHOTO (B-B562-c))
  - Bullock Cabin (PHOTO (C111))
  - "Cavalcade" A Green River Rendezvous (PHOTO (685mi))
  - Chief Black Coal with other Arapahoes waiting to see their president (Arthur) (PHOTO (In2-tri-arap))
  - Chief Truckee (PHOTO (B-T764-c))
  - Chief Washakie (PHOTO (B-W27))
  - Chief Winnemucca (PHOTO (B-W73))
  - Chief Winnemucca, the Paiute who helped bring an end to the Shoshoni uprising (PHOTO (B-W73))
  - Col. W. G. Bullock (PHOTO (B-B876wy))
  - The Crow Dance (PHOTO (In2-da))
  - Decorated Arapaho tepees and Arapaho Indians at St. Louis Fair, 1904-1905. Watanga's tepee is 3rd from left (PHOTO (In2-tri-arap))
  - English Manor on the Laramie Plains: Home of the Sartoris Brothers (PHOTO (M664-m-sart))
  - Evidence of two cultures. A Shoshoko (Kolmako, Elko, Nevada, 1898) wears white man's clothing but retains hair dress and feathers. Note facial tatoo, sometimes practiced by Basin Shoshones (PHOTO (In2-tri-sho))
  - Exterior of Fort Laramie (PHOTO (F775-La))
  - Fergie Mitchell (PHOTO (B-M69fe))
  - First building on the Wheatland Flats (2) (PHOTO (W994-t-whe))
  - Fort Laramie (PHOTO (F775-La))
  - Fort Laramie, 1842 (PHOTO (F775-La))
  - Four Generations of Coopers (PHOTO (B-C785-F))
  - The Ghost Dance. Woman chanting with arms raised, "Inspiration" (PHOTO (In2-da))
  - Gilbert Natchez (PHOTO (B-N192-g))
  - The Great Messiah Dance (Ghost Dance) at the Cheyenne-Arapaho camp near Fort Reno in June, 1890 (PHOTO (In2-da))
  - Horseshoe Station (PHOTO (5t135-hors))
  - Hotel and Eating House, Cheyenne, Wyoming, 1868-1869 (PHOTO (W994-t-ch-hh))
  - "Indians Attacking Butterfield's Overland Dispatch Coach," from a field sketch by Theodore R. Davis. (Reverse side) "Custer's Last Fight," (PHOTO (In2-ba-Lhh))
  - Interior of Fort Laramie. (PHOTO (F775-La))
  - "Jailhouse at the Kelly" (PHOTO (W994-coan-tc))
  - Jim Shaw and grandson, Bobby Gray (PHOTO (B-5h26j))
  - John Enos, guide for Bonneville and Fremont (PHOTO (B-En6))
  - John H. Gordon (PHOTO (B-G656-jh))
  - John Otterby, Magpie, Little Beaver, and Left Hand et al at commemoration of the Battle of the Washita (PHOTO (In2-bat-was))
  - The Johnson County Invaders (PHOTO (W994-jew))
  - Joseph M. Carey, 4th President (WSGA), 1883-1888 (PHOTO (B-C18))
  - Kolmako, Elko Nevada, showing evidence of two cultures. The Western Shoshones, unlike the Northern, sometimes tatooed their faces, 1898 (PHOTO (In2-tri-sh))
  - La Bonte Stage Station in 1863 (PHOTO (5t135-La))
  - Laramie Peak. From oil painting by J. R. Wilson (PHOTO (L32p-wy))
  - Last Black Hills Coach leaving Cheyenne, February 19, 1887 (PHOTO (5t13c))
  - Little Soldier, Weber Ute (Shoshoni) Chief (PHOTO (In2-tri-sh))
  - Lovelock 1896, Shoshoni or Paiute (PHOTO (In2))
  - Medicine man Gwo-wot (man without a wife) blessing a young sun dancer, about 1904 (PHOTO (In2-mm))
  - Michele Portwood, Arapaho, of Riverton, Wyoming, Miss Indian America, 1964-65, 1964-1965 (PHOTO (In2-be))
  - The Moran Ranch (PHOTO (R151-mor))
  - Mountain home of Mr. and Mrs. W. C. Knight (PHOTO (C111))
  - Mr. Al Bowie (PHOTO (B-B679a))
  - Mr. and Mrs. Dave Gordon and daughter, Mary (PHOTO (B-6654-d))
  - Mr. and Mrs. J. S. Krehbiel with (left to right): Cut Nose Woman, Merdie Huggan, Joseph Cook, Yellow Eyes, Effie Mason, and Singing Woman (PHOTO (B-R872-js))
  - Mr. and Mrs. John Hunton by ruins of Officer's Quarters, Fort Laramie (PHOTO (B-H92ju))
  - Mr. and Mrs. R. D. Robinson (PHOTO (B-R566-rd))
  - Mr. and Mrs. Taylor Miller (PHOTO (B-M618-6))
  - Mrs. Al Bowie (2) (PHOTO (B-B679a))
  - Mrs. Karen Togerson and granddaughter, Tillie (PHOTO (B-T272-K))
  - Mrs. Young-Man-Afraid-of-Horses, Sioux, is working on a pair of beaded buckskin moccasins. Pine Ridge Indian Reservation, South Dakota (PHOTO (B-Y85ma))
  - Ned Yates (PHOTO (B-Y272n))
  - Nellie Scott (PHOTO (B-5co85-n))
  - Nel Scott (PHOTO (B-5co85-n))
  - "Old Bedlam" - Fort Laramie (PHOTO (F775-La-b-ch))
  - On the Lower Laramie: Mr. and Mrs. Ned Yates and family (PHOTO (B-Y272n))
  - On the North Laramie (PHOTO (R524-La))
  - Painting of a Peyote ceremony (cut away of tepee showing circle and altar) and water woman at entrance of tepee (PHOTO (In2-re))
  - Paiute. Five males, two sitting, three standing (PHOTO (In2-tri-pia))
  - Paiute. One old man (PHOTO (In2-tri-pia))
  - Paiute. One old woman (PHOTO (In2-tri-pia))
  - Pete Macfarlane (PHOTO (B-M164-p))
  - Pocatello Braves (PHOTO (In2-tri-po))
  - Portugee Phillips Residence at Chugwater. Swan Land and Cattle Co. Headquarters and Stage Station in background (PHOTO (W994-t-chug))
  - Pyramid Lake (PHOTO (L148-pyr))
  - Railroad House, Cheyenne, Wyoming (PHOTO (W994-t-ch-rd))
  - The result of irrigation. A home on one of the irrigated farms (PHOTO (W994-2g))
  - School at Reeder Place (PHOTO (R151-rp))
  - Sheepeater family encamped near head of Medicine Lodge Creek, Idaho (PHOTO (In2-thi-shee))
  - Shoshoni Indian Camp in the Rockies (PHOTO (In2-tri-sh))
  - Shoshoni Indian Family at tepee camp near Fort Washakie, about 1900 (PHOTO (In2-tri-sh))
  - Shoshoni, Sun Dancers, 1895 (PHOTO (In2-tri-sh))
  - Shoshoni Tribal Leaders: Front Row, Dick Washakie, Chief Washakie, and Tigee. Standing, Per-na-go-shia, Pan-Zook, So-pa-gant, and Mat-ta-vish (PHOTO (In2-tri-sh))
  - Shoshoni, Young man, Snake River Agency, Fort Hall Reservation, Idaho (PHOTO (In2-tri-sh))
  - Sibley Peak (PHOTO (M864-rp-sib))
  - South Idaho Treaty - by Charles Christian Nahl (PHOTO (In2-tri-sit))
  - Station and Creek named for La Bonte (PHOTO (5t135-la))
  - Style on the Laramie Plains, the Sartoris Brothers with their four-in-hand (PHOTO (M664-m-sart))
  - T. S. Garrett - bull whacker (PHOTO (B-G192-ts))
  - Taihi, Shoshoni (PHOTO (B-T131))
  - Tendoi (PHOTO (B-T252wi))
  - Tendoi, "The Climber" in costume. Shoshoni, Lemhi Reservation, Idaho (PHOTO (B-T252wi))
  - Tendoi, Shoshoni (PHOTO (B-T252wi))
  - Teschemacher Hotel, Uva (PHOTO (W994-t-uv))
  - Tom Horn in Laramie County Jail (PHOTO (B-H7826))
  - Tyhee (PHOTO (B-T131))
  - Venerable Scots: W. F. Macfarlane (right), Harry Ralston (left), George Mitchell (center) (PHOTO (B-R139h))
  - Virginia Trenholm, authority on the Wind River Indians, stands by poster of Herman St. Clair, a Shoshoni, used abroad by the U. S. Travel Service to advertise travel in this country (PHOTO (B-T723-v))
  - A Visit from Little Raven (PHOTO (B-L721ra))
  - War Dance at Fort Washakie. The Chief stands at left with tomahawk in hand (PHOTO (In2-da-wd))
  - Washakie at his cabin (PHOTO (B-W27))
  - Washakie's band and encampment in southern foothills of Wind River Mts., Wyoming (South Pass) (PHOTO (In2-tri-sh))
  - Washakie's biography [on an animal skin] (2). (PHOTO (B-W27))
  - Western Shoshoni basket makers (PHOTO (In2-tri-sh))
  - "Where the Laramie Flows" (PHOTO (R524-La))
  - Workers of the Sartoris Mine, Keystone (PHOTO (M664-m-59m))
  - Wovoka, the Paiute Prophet whose influence was felt especially at Fort Hall, which became a point of diffusion for his Ghost Dance religion (PHOTO (B-W917))
  - _ayho bull outfit (PHOTO (W125-Frw))
  - _ citizens of Johnson county who reserved a _tnesses at Laramie (PHOTO (W99-coun-jo))
  - Untitled:
    - Digger Mahalas (PHOTO (In2-tri-mah))
    - A Future Miss Indian America (PHOTO (In2-be))
    - Man and woman double exposed against map of Wyoming (PHOTO (B-B644-L))
    - Miss Indian America XI (PHOTO (In2-be))
    - Portait of woman dressed (elegantly) in white (PHOTO (P566-ea-p))
    - Pots (woven), all Shoshoni (PHOTO (In2-arti))
    - Profile of a man (PHOTO (B-H782-L))
    - Wyoming map (4) (PHOTO (W990m))
  - Black and white photographs (5X7) made from slides, labeled as follows:
    - 1) Evidence of prehistoric culture abounds in Wyoming where examples of rock art are found in the Dinwoody area and elsewhere. Petroglyphs showing characters such as these suggest Shoshonean origin, and it is believed that the figures represent the illusive "little people" (the NunumBi) who would shoot invisible arrows of misfourtune at anyone who displeased them (PHOTO (In2-pic) Indian-Pictographs)
    - 2) The term "Spanish Diggings" is a misnomer because there is no proof that the Spaniards entered Wyoming. The flakes you see are near the quarries in the southeastern part of the state. The unidentified, prehistoric Indians came great distances to mine the peculiar quartzite found there, and they scattered "flakes" or chips over approximately 400 square miles in Platte, Goshen, and Niobrara counties (PHOTO (W994) Wyoming)
    - 3) The Medicine Wheel in the Big Horn Mountians near Shell, Wyoming was the shrine of early-day Indians, but the Shoshones and Mountian Crows who were in the area at the beginning of historic time disclaim any knowledge of its significance (PHOTO (In2-medw) Indian-Medicine Wheel)
    - 4) The Shoshonean Sheepeaters of Eastern Idaho and Northwestern Wyoming were, as their name suggests, dependent for food, clothing and shelter on mountain sheep. They were forced into the inaccessible recesses of the mountains by their aggressive neigbors, the "Horse Indians". The Shoshones have a legend that the Sheepeaters were destroyed by a convulsion of nature. On the contrary, they may have found life on the reservation preferable. Togwotee, a medicine man and subchief under Washakie, was the last known Sheepeater though skeletal remains of their tepees and sheep corrals may still be found in Yellowstone Park (PHOTO (In2-tri-shee) Indian-Tribe-Sheepeaters)
    - 5) The Shoshones, who came here first, had a Basin cultural background. The nation is divided into three main divisions: (1) the Western, in Nevada; (2) the Northern, in Idaho, as well as in Montana at the time of the Lewis and Clark Expedition; and (3) the Eastern, in Wyoming. There are serveral small groups, known as southern, in Utah. The Comanches are a splinter group of the Eastern Shoshones, from who they broke away. They migrated southward in the 1700s. Little is known about the Staitans except that they were allies and forerunners of the Cheyennes (PHOTO (In2) Indian)
    - 6) This is a camp of Eastern Shoshones as it might have looked at the time the first white men arrived. The horse was acquired through the Comanches from the Spaniards. In fact, the Shoshones were the first to introduce horses on the Northern Plains of Canada. They took them north on the west side of the Rockies to avoid their enemies (PHOTO (In2-tri-sh) Indian-Tribe-Shoshone)
    - 7) The Arapahoes comprise a splinter group from the Gros Ventres (Big Bellies) in Canada. These two Gros Ventres Indians, of Montana, show how comely they are. In late prehistoric times, the tribe, known under various names, camped along the South Sasketchewan, the "Belly River". Its name probably resulted from a curve in its course. Those in the splinter group, migrating southward through the Crow country, were called "Tattooed People". The Crow word sounded like A-ra-pa-hoe, which might account for their name. There is no "r" in their language (PHOTO (In2-tri-gr) Indian-Tribe-GrosVentre)
    - 8) This is Watanga (Black Coyote), a Southern Arapahoe for whom a town in Oklahoma is named. The tattooes on his chest indicate that he is an Arapahoe. The scars on his arms are a result of flesh sacrifice he made to the sun when his children were dying from a mysterious cause. In the '90's, he was a Ghost Dance leader. That is the reasom he holds the crow, the symbol of the Ghost Dance, on his knee (PHOTO (B-B561-C) Watanga/Black Coyote)
    - 9) This early map shows the lands occupied by the Plains tribes in pink and the Basin in grey. It includes the Shoshones of Wyoming in the Basin area. This was before the Eastern bands had assimilated Plains culture, which was a gradual process (PHOTO (In2) Indian)
    - 10) A more recent map, by the Bureau of Indian Affairs, includes the marginal tribes in the Plains area. The Eastern Shoshones became Plains Shoshones, after having assumed the more dominant culture. Before coming to the northern plains, where the Arapahoes probably roamed before America was discovered, they are believed to have loved in an area north of the Red River of Minnesota (PHOTO (In2) Indian)
    - 11) The Crows were in Northwestern Wyoming when the Arapahoes migrated from the Assiniboine River, in Canada, in the late 1700's. The Kiowa-Apaches were in the Black Hills for a time before the arrival of the Araphoes, who were followed by the Cheyennes. The Kiowas, with their few Apache connections, drifted southward, and the Cheyennes absorbed the Staitans. The Cheyennes, after their arrival in the Black Hills, encouraged the Sioux, who came in ever increasing numbers. The Cheyennes and Arapahoes were closely allied to maintain a balance of power with the Sioux (PHOTO (In2) Indian)
    - 12) The Louisiana Purchase in 1803 added to the area of the United States by about one third. Though unexplored by the white man, it was Indian country. The first white explorers were sent to find a land route to the West Coast (PHOTO (M32-Lp) Map-Louisiana Purchase)
    - 13) Two members of the Lewis and Clark Expedition were of special interest in Wyoming. They were Sacajawea and John Colter. Sacajawea, the Shoshone wife of Charbonneau, the guide for the expedition, carried her baby on a cradleboard, strapped to her back, the full distance to the West Coast from Fort Mandan, North Dakota. In Montana, she encountered her brother, Cameahwait, chief of the Northern Shoshones, and she helped the explorers establish friendly relations. Colter gave such a fantastic description of the geysers and bubbling mud pots he found in Northwestern Wyoming that the name "Colter's Hell" was applied to Yellowstone Park (PHOTO (N213p-yel) National Park-Yellowstone)
    - 14) South Pass, which was discovered by the trappers and traders, was the only route through the mountians known to the emigrants. This picture shows that it resembles a high, wide plain. Throngs went over South Pass to expand the nation (PHOTO (T681-o) Trail-Oregon)
    - 15) Artist - Photographer William H. Jackson shows Smith, Jackson (David E.), and Sublette, blazing the trail for the emigrants to follow (PHOTO (T681-o) Trail-Oregon)
    - 16) Jim Bridger came to Wyoming as a trapper in 1822. Many years later he took his Shoshone wife, Rutta, back to Missouri, renamed her Mary Washakie, and married her in the white man's manner (PHOTO (B-B764-j) Bridger, Jim)
    - 17) This map shows that the Sioux had taken over the Black Hills by 1830. The Arapahoes, followed by the Cheyennes, had drifted southward. The Cheyennes were in the Cheyenne, Wyoming, area and the Arapahoes in Northern Colorado, where the Denver area became their Heartland. The Sioux had pushed the Crows west into the Power River area (PHOTO (In2) Indian)
    - 18) During the Rendezvous Period, the trappers assembled in the peaceful beaver-rich Shoshone country for their trade events. There the trappers, traders and Indians would meet at a specified time and place to exchange commodities and celebrate. All of the rendezvous were held in Shoshone country, with half on Green River and its tributaries (PHOTO (W994) Wyoming)
    - 19) Alfred Jacob Miller, the first great artist to follow the trail, depicts the friendly spirit of the Indians in this picture he called "Shoshone Hospitality" (PHOTO (B-M612aj-p) Miller, Alfred Jacob-Paintings)
    - 20) The Shoshones, as well as the Comanches, were great horsemen. Miller portrays a cavalcade, approaching a Green River Rendezvous. The Chief on the white horse is Moh-woom-ha, Washakie's predecessor (PHOTO (B-M612aj-p) Miller, Alfred Jacob-Paintings)
    - 21) This Miller painting is the only picture extant of old Fort William at the mouth of the Laramie River on the North Platte. It was built in 1834 for permanent trade with the Indians through the rendezvous was not over. The farsighted traders could tell that the future lay in buffalo robes, so they established their trading post in the middle of buffalo country. About the same time, Bent's Fort was founded on the Arkansas River. The two forts were largely reponsible for the two divisions of the Cheyenne and Arapahoe into the Northern and Southern branches. Traders marrying into the tribes acquired not only wives but also their extended families and even their bands (PHOTO (B-M612aj-p) Miller, Alfred Jacob-Paintings)
    - 22) Seven years after Fort William was constructed, the logs had begun to decay, so a more substantial building was erected in the general area though the exact location of the old fort cannot be pinpointed. The new fort, Fort John, was named for John Sarpy, a trader. The original fort was thought to have been named for William Sublette (PHOTO (F775-jo) Fort-John)
    - 23) Moh-woom-ha is shown here wearing a bearclaw necklace which shows that he is a man of distinction. The portrait is by Alfred Jacob Miller (PHOTO (B-M612aj-p) Miller, Alfred Jacob-Paintings)
    - 24) Petroglyphs are usually of an ancient origin, but this may have been made in historic times. It could have been made as recently as 1840, when Father DeSmet baptized at the Treaty Council of 1851. The man holding the two crosses maight have been "The Black Robe", DeSmet. The encirclement suggests a completed story. The Arapahoes did not forget that 300 children were baptized and of that number many died. Their death was blamed on the white man's religion (PHOTO (In2-pic) Indian Pictographs)
    - 25) Fort Laramie, a favorite trading place of the Sioux, was the first settlement in Wyoming; Fort Bridger, in Western Wyoming, the second. Louis Vasquez, Bridger's French-Spanish partner, preferred their establishment in Salt Lake, thus leaving Bridger among the Indians - that is, until trouble resulted when the Mormons accused him of furnishing guns to the Indians to shoot Mormons. He did provide guns for the Shoshones to defend themselves when they went into enemy country fo the Great Treaty Council of 1851. When a warrant was issued for his arrest, he lef the country. His fort was later bought by the Saints and used for a trading post and mail sation (PHOTO (F775-br) Fort-Bridger)
    - 26) This picture shows old Fort John in relation to Fort Laramie, a later name for the same trading post. It was purchased for a military post in 1849 to supply and protect emigrants on the Oregon-Mormon-California Trail (PHOTO (F775-la-dr) Fort-Laramie-Drawings)
    - 27) Fremont Lake was named after General John Charles Fremont, who was popularly known as "the Pathfinder". The paths had been found by the buffalo and the Indians and had b-en clearly defined by the trappers and traders. Fremont made his contribution by mapping the trail. He named the streams and indicated the distance between campsites. He should have been called the "Pathmarker", for he rendered a great service to the emigrants (PHOTO (La148-fre) Lake-Fremont)
    - 28) This map shows the location of tribes at the time of the Great Treaty Council of 1851. By then the Sioux had pushed the Crows from the Powder River country over to the Big Horn and Wind River. This area brought them in conflict with the Shoshones and Bannocks who had considered this their hunting grounds for generations (PHOTO (In2) Indian)
    - 29) This shows more clearly the aboriginal domain of Wyoming's two tribes, the Shoshones and Arapahoes. The Shoshones and Bannocks were to the west and the Cheyennes and Arapahoes "between the rivers" - the Platte and Arkansas (PHOTO (In2) Indian)
    - 30) In 1828, an area in the central part of the United States was designated Indian Territory. Like all Indian lands, it diminished into what was later known as Oklahoma. An effort was made to locate all Indians in this area (PHOTO (In2) Indian)
    - 31) This is the way Oklahoma, or "Indian Territory", looked in 1899. All reservations, with the exception of the Osage, have been terminated. The Osage Indians have kept their lands and their mineral rights, and as a consequence are better off than the other Indian tribes in the state (PHOTO (In2) Indian)
    - 32) Since the Shoshones were merely guests at the Treaty Council of 1851, they had no say regarding the designated areas. They eventually settled their claim to their hunting grounds when they defeated the Crows at the fabled Battle of Crowheart Butte (PHOTO (B981-cro) Butte-Crowheart)
    - 33) In 1857, when it appeared that the Mormons might secede and establish Deseret, an independent empire, Gen. Albert Sidney Johnston was sent west to bring the Saints in line. The so-called Mormon War, which resulted, was actually a "push", with the Mormons "burning their bridges behind them" as they withdrew to Salt Lake. All that Johnston found at Fort Bridger was the stone wall they had so arduously built. After a miserable winter, both the Mormons and the "gentiles" were ready to talk peace. Though the Shoshones have been said to have been neutral, Washakie's patience had been tried by settlers coming into his country. Labeling all as Mormons, he considered this an excellent opportunity to run them out, so he offered 1,200 warriors to the service of the Army for Utah, as Johnston's army was called. His offer was refused, and he lived out his life, pleased by the thought that he had never harmed a white man (PHOTO (F775-br) Fort-Bridger)